door [music]
the West Wing.
He escorts us in straight into the Oval
Office.
There's the president, [music]
the vice president, the national
security adviser, the CIA director, and
then my boss [music] and me. The
president says, "Gentlemen, please sit."
So, we all sit [music] and I'm looking
around and I remember saying to myself,
"My friends [music] would never believe
me if I told them where I was right now.
Never believe me."
So, the president [music] says, "Well,
now what do we do?"
And then everybody [music] turns and
looks at me.
And it took me a second and I said,
"Oh, um Mr. President, as you know,
[music] Iraqi troops I have chills right
now thinking of it, just remembering it.
I said, "Iraqi troops crossed the
Kuwaiti border
uh at 2:00 in the morning. They seized
[music] the entirety of Kuwait. The
royal family has fled to Saudi Arabia,
you know, blah blah blah blah."
And he says, [music]
"Do we know who is in charge in Kuwait
right now?" I said, "Yes, sir, we do.
The Iraqis made an announcement that Dr.
Ahmed Khatib uh is now the occupation
governor of Iraq."
"Do we know anything about him?" I said,
"Yes, sir." I had actually written an
article about him a month earlier just
because he was interesting [music] to
me.
I said, "Yes, sir. He's a medical
doctor.
>> [music]
>> He hates the royal family because his
mother was a slave
uh in the household of the royal family.
They had slavery until 1955 [music]
in the uh on the Arabian Peninsula. So,
[music] I said, "She's a Sudanese slave
uh to sort of make up for it. Once
slavery ended, they [music] sent Ahmed
to the American University of Beirut. He
trained there as a doctor.
>> [music]
>> But, his college roommate was George
Habash
and together [music] they founded the
Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine."
And the vice president says, "Jesus
Christ!" Like that.
And the president just goes like this
and he says, [music] "Gentlemen, thank
you.
That'll be enough.
I need to think about this."
Well, later that afternoon, Margaret
Thatcher [music]
famously now called him.
He genuinely didn't know what to do.
>> [music]
>> Yeah, and you're talking about Papa
Bush. Papa Bush. Yeah. And she said,
"George, now's not the time to go
wobbly."
Next thing [music] you know,
we have six aircraft carrier battle
groups on on their way to the Gulf,
quarter of a million ground troops,
and we liberated
>> [music]
>> Kuwait February 1991.
Wow. Wow. And and you played a role in
that at How were you 30 yet?
>> I was 26.
And did And did you Was there any part
of you that's like, "I shouldn't be
here. I don't really know what I'm
saying"?
>> Oh, everybody has imposter syndrome. All
of us did. I remember thinking,
you know,
"Why me? Who am I? I'm just some guy
from Pennsylvania."
And here I am sitting with the
president, telling the president what to
do?
But, you know, I I liked it. I enjoyed
it. It was exciting.
I was on a plane once from
Milan
to Sofia, Bulgaria.
I never talk to people on planes. I
just, you know, put in my earbuds, read
a book, whatever. You did that purposely
not to blow your Not to blow my cover.
Okay.
And there's this guy next to me, this
Italian guy and he's blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah the whole flight and
and I'm trying to give him one-word
answers and what they taught us in
training is
they ask you what you do for a living,
just tell them something that's so
boring that they don't ask follow-up
questions. [laughter] Cuz usually I'd
say,
"Oh, I'm involved in training. We we
train people, you know, who do
international trade and import-export."
And And people are like, "Oh, that
sounds great." And then that's the end
of it. So, this guy ta ta ta ta ta
Finally, I said,
"Okay, look.
I smuggle women and cigarettes from
Eastern Europe. Are you happy now?"
And he goes, "Well,
I don't think I approve." I said, "I
didn't ask you approval."
And then he just kind of sat there like
this the rest of the flight and I
thought to myself, "Finally."
>> [laughter]
>> But, at least I didn't blow my cover.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Hey guys, I think a bunch of
you know that I'm on a health journey
these days. I'm trying to cook
different, maybe trying to exercise a
little bit differently, trying to walk
more, even trying to sleep better. But,
even with all of that, my favorite
cousin kept pushing me. She said, "You
should consider supplements." And if I'm
honest, I was a little bit hesitant. I
don't know whether it's because I was
busy or that I just didn't want more
stuff in my body. But, recently I found
something really beautiful. If you
haven't tried Dose before, this is a
wonderful supplement. It's about 2 oz. A
lot of folks say it tastes like mango
but with a little bit of kick in it.
It's got beautiful things like turmeric
and ginger and lemon, all sorts of
goodness in it and it's great if you've
got cholesterol issues like yours truly
or even if you're just thinking about
kind of general liver health. Look, I'm
no doctor but I know that good stuff is
good stuff and so I hope you'll consider
this and if you do, tell them that
Carlos sent you. Go ahead and get 35%
off. Enjoy it. Enjoy it and enjoy it.
And so, your rising Are you on your way
to becoming the director of the CIA?
Yeah, I wish. I mean I mean were you on
that trajectory? Like would Like Like
would someone reviewing the the rising
young superstars have have tabbed you as
one of the rising young superstars?
>> No, that is a very very political
position and there've only been
three, I guess, directors over the years
who were career CIA officers. Everybody
else has been an outsider. The former
FBI director, lots of generals, which I
think is always like historically been a
big mistake.
>> And why would they want generals?
I don't know. You get four shiny stars
on your shoulder and they think that
you're Superman, you can do anything.
And it was my experience that
people became four-star generals by
saying, "Yes, sir."
You don't want somebody in that position
to say, "Yes, sir." You want somebody in
that position who can say, "Mr.
President, let me tell you why that's a
terrible idea."
Right? You need somebody with the the
wherewithal to stand up to the policy
makers. So, it's so clear to me that you
still love and revere the work that you
did and that you were one of the
fortunate people in this life who
actually got to do something that they
both dreamed of.
>> I thoroughly enjoyed my career. Yeah,
you you you enjoyed it. But,
after 9/11,
everybody went nuts.
They just went nuts.
They acted like
the law, whether domestic or or
international, meant nothing to us. We
were the good guys. We had been wronged.
We were going to take revenge.
And you're either with us or you're
against us. And if you're against us,
then get out. I know that torture and
the question around torture ends up
becoming a place where you you you raise
your hand and where you object and I
know that that ultimately metastasized.
But, just give us a version of that for
people who don't know the story. Well, I
was one of 14 people asked if I wanted
to be trained in the use of what they
called enhanced interrogation
techniques. I was the only one of the 14
who said no. I believed it was illegal.
Besides being immoral and unethical, I
thought it was illegal. It was illegal.
It was clearly illegal. Any can
read the law that we wrote, the the
federal torture act of 1946. Anybody can
read the the United Nations Convention
Against Torture and Cruel and Inhumane
Treatment.
And
I mean it it doesn't get any clearer
clearer than that.
>> Take me Take me through torture. So,
you're one of 14 people who they asked
they they ask, "Do you want to get
trained in this?" And you're like, "No,
it's illegal." Take Take me. Yeah.
Buddy of mine uh in the Counterterrorism
Center who happened to be
a psychiatrist, MD, PhD, and a brigadier
general in the Army.
And we go to the same church. We're in
the same men's group. He said to me one
day, "Buddy, you know, um you know they
call you the human rights guy behind
your back."
And I said, "Yeah, I know."
And he said, "You know that's not a
compliment, right?"
And I said, "Steve, I'm right
and they're wrong
and I'm comfortable with my position."
Well,
that was not the popular position to
take.
And so,
they kind of squeezed me out. But, I had
done so well in Pakistan that I became
the executive assistant to the deputy
director for operations.
So, um
my career just continued
to go straight up.
>> So, that was a big deal though to raise
your hand on a question of principle.
>> one. And you And your career still keeps
going well? Because I had a rabbi
who
My dad My dad always says that. My dad
always says, "You don't need a mentor.
You need a rabbi or an angel."
>> That's it. Yeah. He sat above the guys
making these torture decisions.
And he said, "Don't worry about it." He
said, "You did the right thing." He
called it a slippery slope. He said,
"You know how these guys are. Somebody's
going to kill a prisoner and then
they're going to go to they're going to
go to prison."
And what exactly were they doing? Like
I've heard the word waterboarding. But,
like for someone who again has never
been in Okay, so let's say you are
laying on this slab of of granite right
here, but it's slightly elevated so your
feet are a little bit higher than your
than your head. They'll wrap your your
face and head in material,
a towel, you know, whatever,
tie you down so you can't move,
and then pour water on your face.
So, water gets in your mouth, you you to
drown.
W- In the case of Abu Zubaydah, he
actually did drown his